In this video, we're going to look at another global analysis called liveness
在这段视频中，我们将查看另一个名为活跃度的全球分析
analysis. So, in the past several videos we've looked at a procedure for globally
分析。因此，在过去的几个视频中，我们查看了全球范围内
propagating constants through a control flow graph And let's, here's, here's one
在控制流图中传播常量，下面是一个
of the control flow graphs we've been looking at and recall that this algorithm
我们一直在看的控制流图，回想一下这个算法
that we discussed would be sufficient to show that we could replace this use of x
我们所讨论的将足以表明我们可以替换x的这种用法。
here by the constant three. And once we do that. This assignment x might no longer be
在这里按固定的三。一旦我们做到了这一点。此赋值x可能不再是
useful. It might not be used anywhere And so we could potentially delete this
很有用。它可能不会在任何地方使用，因此我们可能会将其删除
statement from the program And that would be a real optimization, an important
语句，这将是一个真正的优化，一个重要的
optimization to do. However, we can only do that if x is not used elsewhere in the
要做的优化工作。但是，我们只能在x没有在其他地方使用的情况下才能做到这一点。
program. So let's be a little more careful about what we mean by saying that x is not
程序。所以让我们更小心一点，我们说x不是
used. So down here is a use of x, a reference to x, in a statement. And,
使用。下面是x的用法，引用x，在语句中。和,
clearly this particular reference to x, is, use, picking up the value that's
显然，这个对x的特殊引用是，使用，提取的值是
defined by this right x here. So, we say that the right of x here, is live. This
这里由这个右边的x定义。所以，我们说x在这里的权利，是活的。这
one is live. Okay, And what that means is that the value may be used in the future.
一个是现场直播。好的，这意味着这个值可能会在未来使用。
So, live, equals, may be used. In the future, Okay? So the value written to x at
所以，LIVE，EQUACES，可以使用。在未来，好吗？因此，写入x的值在
this line of code maybe used by some subsequent instruction And here it's not
这行代码可能会被一些后续指令使用，但这里没有
just that it may be used. It's actually guaranteed to be used because there's only
只是说它可能会被使用。它实际上被保证会被使用，因为只有
one path. And that one path has a reference to x on it before there's
一条路。这一条路径上有一个对x的引用
another assignment to x. Okay? So this particular value of x as written here is
另一个任务给x。好吗？所以这里写的x的这个特定值是
guaranteed to be used. But in general we don't require that. We just mean there has
保证会被使用。但一般说来，我们并不要求这样做。我们的意思是有
to be a possibility that it will be used. Now in contrast let's take a look at this.
它有可能会被使用。现在对比一下，我们来看看这个。
Other statement in this example, Here, we assign x a value three but this assignment
在本例中的其他语句中，在这里，我们为x赋值为3，但此赋值
x, this value of x is never used. This one, is dead. Alright? Because the value
x，则永远不会使用此值x。这一个，已经死了。好吗？因为它的价值
three here is overwritten by the value four before there's any use of, the
此处的3在使用之前被值4覆盖，
variable x, Okay? So this particular right to x will never see the light of day.
变量x，好吗？因此，这种对x的特殊权利将永远不会出现在光天化日之下。
It'll never get used by any part of the program. And we say that it is dead. So,
它永远不会被程序的任何部分使用。我们说它死了。所以,
to summarize a variable x is live as a statement S if, there exist some statement
总而言之，变量x是作为语句Sif活动的，存在一些语句
that uses x. Okay. So, some other statement S prime that uses x, and there
它使用x。好的。所以，其他一些使用x的语句S素数，在那里
is some path from S to S prime and there is no intervening assignments on that path
是从S到S素数的某条路径，且在该路径上没有中间赋值
to x. Alright? So, there needs to be an assignment to x, at some statement S there
敬x，好吗？所以，需要对x进行赋值，在某个语句S处
is some path through the program that reaches a read of x. Add sum statement to
是通过程序到达读取x的某个路径。将SUM语句添加到
S prime, and along that path, there is no right to x, Okay? And if this situation
素数，沿着这条路径，没有x的权利，好吗？如果这种情况
arises, then we say that this value written in this first statement s is live.
出现，那么我们就说第一个语句s中写的这个值是活的。
Now if a value is not live, then it is dead. And a statement that assigns to x is
现在，如果一个值不是活的，那么它就是死的。赋值给x的语句是
going to be dead code if x is dead after the assignment. So, if we know that
如果x在赋值后是死的，那么它就是死代码。所以，如果我们知道
immediately after the assignment, immediately after this assignment to x,
紧接着赋值之后，紧接着这个赋值给x，
there is no possibility that a value of x will be used in the future. Well then the
未来不可能使用x值。那好吧，那么
assignment was useless, and the entire statement can be removed. Alright, So dead
赋值是无用的，可以删除整个语句。好吧，那就死定了
assignments can be deleted from the program, But notice that in order to do
可以从程序中删除工作分配，但请注意，为了做到这一点
that we have to have the liveness information. We need to know whether x is
我们必须要有活体信息。我们需要知道x是否
dead at this point. So, once again, what we want to do is to have global
在这一点上已经死了。所以，再一次，我们要做的是让全球
information about the control flow graph. In this case, the property is whether x
有关控制流图的信息。在本例中，属性是x是否为x
will be used in the future. We want to make that information local to a specific
将在未来使用。我们希望将该信息设置为特定的本地信息
point in the program, so we can make a local optimization decision. Alright, And
在程序中定位，这样我们就可以做出局部优化决策。好的，还有
just like for constant propagation, we're going to define in a, an algorithm for
就像常量传播一样，我们要在一个中定义一个算法，
performing liveness analysis And it's going to follow the same framework. If
进行活跃度分析，它将遵循相同的框架。如果
we're going to express liveness in terms of information transferred between
我们要用信息传递的方式来表达我们的生命力
adjacent statements, just as we did for copy of constant propagation And it's
相邻语句，就像我们对常量传播的副本所做的那样，它的
gonna turn out that liveness is actually quite, If it's simpler, or somewhat
我会发现，如果更简单的话，活跃度实际上是相当高的，或者有点
simpler, than constant propagation, since it's just a Boolean property. Eh, you
比常量传播简单，因为它只是一个布尔属性。嗯，你
know, it's either true of false. Alright So let's take a look at some of the rules
要知道，要么是真的，要么是假的。好的，那么让我们来看看其中的一些规则
for liveness. So here, we're defining what it means for x to be live at this point
为了活泼。所以在这里，我们定义了x在这一点上活着意味着什么
here. So we're immediately after p is x live And it's going to be live. Remember
这里。所以我们紧接着p是x实况转播，它将是实况转播。记住
what the intuition is. The intuition is that a, the variable x is live right after
直觉是什么。直觉是a，变量x紧随其后
p if the value of x is used on some path. On one of the paths that begin at p.
如果x的值在某条路径上使用，则为p。在其中一条从p开始的路径上。
Alright, And so, in order to know whether it's live, we're going to take the
好的，为了知道是不是实况转播，我们要
liveness information at each of the input points. So that would be here, here, here,
每个输入点的活跃度信息。所以它应该在这里，
and here. So each of the successor statements after p And we're gonna ask, is
还有这里。所以p后面的每个后续声明，我们要问的是
x live at any of those points? So it's just a big or over the liveness of x and
X住在这些地方吗？所以这只是一个很大的或超过x的活性
all of the successors of p And that's the liveness of x at the out of p. Next, let's
所有p的后继者，这就是x在出界p的活跃度，接下来，让我们
consider the effect of individual statements on the liveness of x. So, the
考虑单个语句对x的活性的影响。因此，
first rule is, that if we have a statement, and it reads the value of x,
第一条规则是，如果我们有一个语句，它读取x的值，
Okay? So here, we have an assignment statement, and on the right hand side, it
好吧?在这里，我们有一个赋值语句，在右边，它
refers to x, so its reading x Then, x is live Before that statement. Clearly, x is
是指x，所以它的读数是x，那么x在该语句之前是有效的。显然，x是
just about to be used on the end of this statement, and so x is live at that point.
即将在这条语句的末尾使用，所以x在这一点是有效的。
Alright? So if a statement, or if, if a statement reads the
好吗？因此，如果一条语句，或者如果一条语句读取
value of x, then the in of that statement, x, is true. Sorry, the liveness of x is
值，则该语句的in为真。抱歉，x的活性是
true. A second case is when a statement writes the value of x So here we have an
没错。第二种情况是语句写入x的值，因此在这里我们有一个
assignment to x And the rest of the statement does not refer x Does not read
赋值给x并且睡觉的语句没有引用x没有读到
the value of x. So there's no x in E. Okay So in this situation x is not live before
x的值，所以在E中没有x。好的，在这种情况下，x在
the statement. X is not live or we can say that x is dead Before the statement And
这份声明。x不是活的，或者我们可以说x在语句之前是死的，
why is that? Well, we're overriding the value of x, so whatever value, x had
为什么会这样呢？我们覆盖了x的值，所以不管x有什么值
before this statement is never gonna be read. Okay, Because the ee here, the
在这份声明永远不会被宣读之前。好的，因为在座的人，
right-hand side of the assignment, doesn't refer to x And, so, immediately before the
赋值的右侧没有引用x，因此紧接在
statement, the current value of x is never gonna be used in the future. And so x is
语句，则x的当前值将永远不会在将来使用。所以x是
dead at that point. And finally, the last case is what if we have a statement that
在这一点上已经死了。最后，最后一个例子是，如果我们有一个声明，
does not refer to x? Okay, So it neither reads no r writes x. Well, then whatever
不是指x吗？好的，所以它既不是不是r写的是x。好的，那不管怎么说
the line this is of x after the statement, it has the same liveness, before this
这是语句后面的x行，它具有相同的活性，在此之前
statement. So if x is live here. Then x will be live here. Okay, and similarly, if
声明。所以如果x住在这里。那么x就会住在这里。好的，同样的，如果
x is dead After the statement. Then x must be dead before the statement. And that's
X在声明之后就死了。那么x在语句之前一定是死的。那就是
because x if x is not use in the future after the statement S then it still want
因为x如果x在语句S之后不在将来使用，那么它仍然希望
be use in the future before the statement S. Since the statement S neither reads nor
用于将来，放在语句S之前。因为语句S既不读也不读
write x. So those are the only four rules and now I can give the algorithm. So
写x，这是仅有的四条规则，现在我可以给出算法了。所以
initially we left the liveness information for x be false at all program points And
最初，我们在所有程序点将x的活性信息保留为false
then we repeat the following until all the statements satisfy the rules one through
然后，我们重复下面的操作，直到所有语句都满足规则1到
four, and just has it's the same algorithm that we used for constant propagation. We
四个，它和我们用来进行常量传播的算法是一样的。我们
pick some statement where the information is inconsistent and then up, update the
选择一些信息不一致的语句，然后向上更新
information at that statement with the appropriate rule. So let's do a simple
该语句中信息和适当的规则。所以让我们做一个简单的
example, something with a loop. So let's begin, say by initializing x to zero, and
例如，有循环的东西。那么让我们开始吧，比方说把x初始化为0，
then what should our loop body do? Well, we can check whether x is equal to ten,
那么我们的循环体应该做什么呢？嗯，我们可以检查x是否等于10，
and if it is, we'll, we'll exit, the loop And let's assume that x is dead on exit.
如果是，我们就退出循环，假设x在退出时是死的。
So x is not refer to outside of the loop. In other wise if x is not ten Then we will
所以x不是指循环之外的。换句话说，如果x不是10，那么我们就会
increment x and we'll branch back to the top of the loop. So this is a very, very
递增x，我们将分支回到循环的顶部。所以这是一个非常非常
silly little program. It just counts to ten and then exits. Well let's do the
愚蠢的小程序。它只需数到十就退出了。好的，让我们来做
lightness now to see where x is life. So since x is dead here on exit it's clearly
现在来看看x在哪里是生命。所以由于x在出口是死的，所以很明显
gonna be dead on the out Of, of this, conditional on this branch, Okay? So I
在这根树枝的条件下，就会死掉，好吗？所以我
should say that x is not live. So we're using booleans here, so that's x's,
应该说x不是活的。所以我们这里用的是布尔值，所以这是x的，
liveness would be false And we're assuming And x is also, not live everyplace else,
活性是假的，我们假设x也是，并不是生活在其他地方，
initially. Okay And so, there's a program point in there, also Where the liveness of
最初是这样的。好的，这里有一个程序点，还有一个活跃度
x is false. Okay, So now, let's propagate the information. Well, so here we have
X为假。好的，那么现在，让我们把信息传播出去。好的，所以我们这里有
read of x. And let me switch colors here. So here we have a read of x. So in fact
读一下x，让我在这里切换颜色。所以这里我们有一个x的读数。所以实际上
the information's inconsistent here because ri ght before this statement since
这里的信息不一致，因为在此语句之前
we have a read of x, x must be live. So in fact, x is live at this point. Now notice
我们看到x的读数了，x肯定是带电的。所以实际上，x在这一点上是活的。现在请注意
that this statement both reads and writes x. Okay? But the rule that says x is live
这个声明既读又写x，好吗？但是说x是实况的规则
before, when we do a read, takes priority here Because, the read happens before the
之前，当我们执行读取时，在这里优先，因为读取发生在
write. So we'll read the old value of x, before we write the new value of x, Okay.
写。所以在我们写x的新值之前，我们先读出x的旧值，好的。
So the old value of x does get used, and that's why x is live immediately before
所以x的旧值确实会被使用，这就是为什么x在紧接之前是有效的
this statement. Okay, so then here's another, read of x. Okay, so on the, so
这份声明。好的，这是另一个，读一下x。好的，所以
the point immediately before this when I left out one program point here, x is also
紧接在此之前的点，我在这里省略了一个程序点，x也是
Y. Okay, And then following edges backwards, well, that means x is gonna be
好的，然后沿着边缘向后，这意味着x将是
live on the back edge of the loop And it's also gonna be live by going into the
在环路的后缘现场直播，它也将通过进入
initialization block. Alright? Now we come back around here and we see that we're
初始化挡路。好吗？现在我们回到这里，我们看到我们是
done 'cause x is already known to be, live within the loop body. And now, live, x is
这样做是因为已经知道x在循环体内，而现在，live，x是
also live here And then the question is, you know, what about this point on, the
也住在这里，然后问题是，你知道，关于这一点，
entrance, at the entrance to the control flow graph? Well, there's a right of x And
入口，在控制流图的入口处？嗯，这里有一个x的右边，
with no read of x on the right-hand side. So, in fact, x, is not live on entry to
右手边没有x的读数。所以，事实上，x并不是在进入
this control flow graph. So in fact, x is dead at this point. So whatever value x
此控制流程图。所以实际上，x在这一点上是死的。所以不管x值是多少
has when we enter the control flow graph, it will never be used in the future.
当我们进入控制流图时，它将永远不会在未来使用。
Alright, and so that is the correct liveness information for every
好的，这就是正确的活体信息
program point in this example. Now another thing you can see from our little example
本例中的程序点。现在，您可以从我们的小示例中看到另一件事
is that values change from false to true, but not the other way around. So every
就是值从假变成真，但不是反过来。所以每个人
value starts at false, and it can change at most once. To say that the value is
值从false开始，最多只能更改一次。要说它的价值是
actually live, the property becomes true, and then it won't ever change back to
实实在在的生活，财产变成真实的，然后它就再也不会变回
false again. So, going back to orderings, We only have two values in this analysis,
又是假的。所以，回到排序，我们在这个分析中只有两个值，
false and true And the ordering is that false is less than true. Okay, And we
FALSE和TRUE，顺序是FALSE小于TRUE。好的，我们
know, so everything starts at the lowest possible element of the ordering and they
知道吗，所以所有事情都从排序中尽可能低的元素开始
only move up, and so they can be promoted to true, but no t vice versa And so since
只有向上移动，它们才能提升为真，反之亦然，因为
each value can only change once, termination is guaranteed. That eventually
每个值只能更改一次，保证终止。那最终会是
we're guaranteed to have consistent information throughout the control flow
我们保证在整个控制流中具有一致的信息
graph, and the analysis will terminate.
图形，则分析将终止。